Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos Papers, 1960-1998 and undated, bulk 1975-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos papers 1960-1998 and undated bulk 1975-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
18.6 linear feet Extent: 11625 Items
Rena Bartos worked as a marketing researcher, advertising executive, and consultant from 1960 to 1998. She directed research at the McCann Erickson advertising agency and held the position of Senior Vice President at the J. Walter Thompson Company before forming her own marketing consulting firm, The Rena Bartos Company. A pioneer in the field of marketing to women and an advocate for older adult consumers, Bartos was the recipient of numerous prestigous marketing and advertising industry awards, including the Matrix and Effie Awards. The Rena Bartos Papers consists of speeches and presentations, publications, research, and correspondence related to Bartos' career in the marketing research divisions of McCann Erickson and the J. Walter Thompson Company, spanning the years 1960-1998, with the bulk of the contents from 1975-1991. Other items in the collection include video and audio copies of speeches and presentations by Bartos, a brief history of the J. Walter Thompson Company, as well as drafts of articles and manuscripts.
RL.00664
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rena Bartos Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1985-1997.
Biographical Note
1939 Graduated Cum Laude from Rutgers University
1964-1966 Director of Research, McCann Erickson
1966 Joined J. Walter Thompson as Head of Creative Research
1975 YWCA Salute to Women in Business Award New York Chapter of Women in Communications Matrix Award
1976 Advertising and Consumers: New Perspectives published
1977 Named Senior Vice President at J. Walter Thompson Company The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research: A Tribute by the Advertising Research Foundation published in the Journal of Advertising Research
1978 What Every Marketer Should Know About Women from the Harvard Business Review selected as a finalist for 1979 National Magazine Award
1979 Named Advertising Woman of the Year by Advertising Women of New York
1982 The Moving Target: What Every Marketer Should Know About Women published Named one of the 100 Most Important Women by Ladies Home Journal
1983 First female Chairperson of the Advertising Research Council
1985 Named Boston Professional Chapter of Women in Communications Matrix Award
1987 Inducted into the Market Research Hall of Fame Retired from J. Walter Thompson to form The Rena Bartos Company
1989 Marketing to Women Around the World published in the United States. It would later be published in Germany and Great Britain Named President of the Market Research Council
Collection Overview
The Rena Bartos Papers span the years 1960-1998, with the bulk of the material dating from 1975 to 1991. The collection documents Bartos' career through speeches and presentations, publications, correspondence, research files, slides, photographs and videotapes, while in positions at McCann Erickson, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), and The Rena Bartos Company. Major topics include marketing to under-represented groups, the role of women in advertising, and Bartos' efforts to promote marketing towards women and over forty-nine adults. The collection is organized into five series and two indexes: Speeches and Presentations; Correspondence; Publications; Research Files; Audiovisual Materials; an Alphabetical List of Publications; and an Alphabetical List of Speech Titles
The Speeches and Presentations Series includes reading copies or scripts from speeches and presentations given by Bartos during her career. Dominant themes include the role of women in advertising, marketing to underrepresented groups such as women and people in Latin America and India, and the psychological aspects of advertising. In addition, the series includes the slides and graphics Bartos used in her speeches, as well as press clippings from her various speaking engagements.
The Correspondence Series includes business correspondence, mailings and solicitations from Bartos' career in marketing research, as well as correspondence with JWT executives, including Don Johnston and Thomas Sutton. The series also contains correspondence between Bartos and the various publishers of her written works.
The Publications Series includes copies of the articles written by Bartos for scholarly and trade publications such as The Harvard Business Review, the Journal of Advertising Research, Marketing Review, and Marketing and Research Today, either from the original periodical or in pre-print form.
The Research Series includes an extensive collection of newspaper and periodical clippings and other resources used by Bartos as supporting materials for her speaking engagements, articles, and books.
The Audiovisual Materials Series includes audio and visual recordings of promotional works for marketing campaigns, including The Moving Target. In addition, this series also includes tapes of speeches and interviews given by Bartos, some of which relate to the published article The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in these collections in the JWT Archives: the Albert B. Stridsberg Papers, the Thomas Sutton Papers, the Don Johnston Papers, and the Joseph O'Donnell Papers.
Subject Headings
Bartos, Rena; Johnston, Don; Sutton, Thomas (Thomas Francis); J. Walter Thompson Company; McCann-Erickson Worldwide; Rena Bartos Company; Bartos, Rena. Moving target; Advertising; Advertising -- Awards; Advertising -- Psychological aspects; Advertising executives; Aged consumers -- United States; Marketing; Marketing -- India; Marketing -- Latin America; Market research; Minorities in advertising; Women consumers -- United States; Women in advertising; Clippings; Photographs; Slides; Speeches; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Speech and Presentation Series, 1960-1998 and undated, (11 boxes)
  Consists of copies of speeches and some working scripts (where available) for presentations and addresses delivered by Bartos between 1962 and 1998. In addition, the series also includes speeches from various JWT executives, slides and graphics used by Bartos during her presentations, and clippings and ephemera from her speaking engagements and career milestones. Series is organized into two subseries: Speeches and Supporting Materials.
  - Speeches Subseries, 1960-1998 and undated
    Includes speeches and presentations given by Bartos during her career. A chronological list of speeches is located in Box 5. The speeches are arranged chronologically to preserve their original order; an alphabetical listing of speech titles appears at the end of the finding aid.
    - Chronological file of speeches
      - 1962-1982, (34 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1982-1984, (32 folders) (Box 2)
      - 1984-1986, (32 folders) (Box 3)
      - 1986-1990, (18 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1990-1998 and undated, (22 folders) (Box 5)
    - Chronological list of speeches (printed list in folder), 1962-1998 and undated (Box 5)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company executive speeches, 1960-1980s and undated (Box 5)
  - Supporting Materials Subseries, 1966-1995 and undated
    Includes graphics, slides, and press files from Bartos' speaking engagements. Some of the files relate to various projects and presentations that Bartos produced, but actual dates cannot be determined for many items.
    - Graphics, 1971-1990 and undated (Box 5)
      Primarily statistical charts and drafts of data presentations. Arranged alphabetically.
      - Adult trends, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - All titles, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Baby boomers, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - Canada, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
      - Challenging our assumptions, undated (Box 5)
      - Colorless slides, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Consumer opportunities, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Credibility, circa 1985 (Box 5)
      - Detroit auto dealers, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
      - Facts of life, 1990 (Box 5)
      - International moving target, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Japan, 1980-1986 (Box 5)
      - Latin America, 1990, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Marketing to women around the world, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Media, 1985-1986, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Moving target, 1990 (Box 5)
      - MRB (Market Research Britain)-Great Britain, 1971-1986 (Box 5)
      - New demographics, undated (Box 6)
      - Over 49 market, 1990 (Box 6)
      - Women, 1985-1988, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous
        - General, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
        - International, 1987-1991, (2 folders) (Box 6)
        - Verbals/Visuals, undated (Box 6)
    - Press files, 1966-1995 and undated
      Newspaper and periodical clippings about Bartos' career. Arranged alphabetically.
      - Book reviews for Marketing to Women Around the World, 1988-1991, (4 folders) (Box 6)
      - Brazil, 1980, 1989, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Effie Awards, 1976-1995 (Box 6)
      - Press files, 1966-1973, (7 folders) (Box 6)
      - Press files, 1974-1987, (17 folders) (Box 7)
      - Press files, 1988-1995 and undated, (7 folders) (Box 8)
    - Slides, undated
      Slides for Bartos' speaking engagements. Dates cannot be accurately determined. Arranged alphabetically.
      - ARF (Advertising Research Foundation) (Box 8)
      - Baby boomers
        - Media (Box 8)
        - Products (Box 8)
        - Extras (Box 8)
      - Changing face of fashion (Box 8)
      - Credibility (Box 8)
      - Detroit (Box 8)
      - ERA (Equal Rights Ammendment), (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - box 9 (Box 9)
      - Facts of life, (3 folders) (Box 9)
      - Financial (Box 9)
      - JWT Board Meeting, 5, November 1982 (Box 9)
      - Marketing to women around the world, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Media (Box 9)
      - Miscomprehension I (Box 9)
      - Miscomprehension II (Box 9)
      - Over forty-nine, (2 folders)
        - Advertising imagery (Box 9)
        - Extras, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - Pacific Rim (Box 10)
      - Physical fitness (Box 10)
      - Research and development presentation (Box 10)
      - Scottsdale (Box 10)
      - Weight concern (Box 10)
      - Women, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - Women and the car market (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
        - Graphs (Box 10)
        - Updates (Box 10)
        - Verbals, (3 folders) (Box 11)
        - Visuals, (7 folders) (Box 11)
- Correspondence Series, 1971-1995 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Includes correspondence and memoranda that document Bartos' involvement in a range of market research activities, including JWT's Special Markets project, marketing to women and minorities, and Bartos' own Moving Target project. Also included is correspondence that details the career of Joseph O'Donnell. The series is organized into two subseries: J. Walter Thompson Company Subseries and The Rena Bartos Company Subseries and chronologically therein.
  - J. Walter Thompson Company Subseries, 1971-1995 and undated
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1971-1977, (24 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1978-1987, (14 folders) (Box 12)
      Folders 1985-1987 contain information on JWT executive Joseph O'Donnell.
    - 1981-1995 and undated, Correspondence with Tom Sutton (Box 12)
      Sutton (1923-1994) was Executive Vice President of JWT until his retirement in 1983.
  - The Rena Bartos Company Subseries, 1988-1995 and undated
    - 1988-1991, (6 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1992-1995 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
- Publications Series, 1966-1995 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Consists of copies of newspaper and periodical articles written by Bartos during her career and various internal reports Bartos created for the J. Walter Thompson Company, including What Every Marketer Should Know About Women for The Harvard Business Review and Qualitative Research: What Is It and Where Did It Come From? for The Journal of Advertising Research. In addition, the series contains articles from various JWT Company publications documenting the history of the company, including the attempted takeover of the company by Joseph O'Donnell in 1986, and transcripts of two interviews with Bartos. The series is organized into two subseries: Personal Publications and J. Walter Thompson Company History.
  - Personal Publications Subseries, 1967-1995 and undated
    Includes articles, reports and drafts written by Bartos. Arranged alphabetically. An alphabetical index of Bartos' publications appears at the end of the finding aid.
    - Drafts, undated (Box 13)
    - Interview transcripts, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company reports, 1967-1986, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Publications, 1973-1995 and undated
      - 1973-1984, (11 folders) (Box 13)
      - 1985-1995 and undated, (8 folders) (Box 14)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company History Subseries, circa 1966-1987 and undated
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Annual reports, 1970-1979 (Box 14)
    - Articles relating to company history, 1966-1987 (Box 14)
      Includes articles on the attempted takeover of the J. Walter Thompson Company by Joseph O'Donnell in 1986.
    - Newsletters, 1966-1986, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Photographs, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
- Research Series, circa 1960-1996 and undated, (14 boxes)
  Consists of newspaper clippings, periodical articles, interview transcripts, and papers published by other marketing researchers which were used by Bartos during her career. Includes page proofs and research for books and articles, including The Moving Target, Marketing to Women Around the World, Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market and What Every Marketer Should Know About Women from The Harvard Business Review. Organized into two subseries: Clippings and Documents and Published Materials.
  - Clippings and Documents Subseries, circa 1960-1995 and undated
    Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, typed reports, trade brochures and drafts of reports collected to oprovide background and context for Bartos' writings. Arranged alphabetically.
    - AAAA (American Association of Advertising Agencies) advertising careers, 1960 and undated (Box 15)
    - Advertising and women, 1978-1995 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Aging, 1978-1980 and undated (Box 15)
    - American consumers, 1977-1982 (Box 15)
    - Attitudes towards advertisers, undated (Box 15)
    - Baby boomers, 1975-1990 and undated
      - General, 1975-1990 (Box 15)
      - Backups, 1975-1990 (Box 15)
      - Illustrations, 1975-1989 and undated (Box 15)
    - Barbara Bryant, 1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      Includes articles written by marketer Barbara Bryant, of the Heritage Society.
    - Changes in womens lives, 1979-1981
      - General, 1979-1980, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      - Phenomenon of women's work, 1979-1981 (Box 15)
      - Types of women's work, 1979-1981, (4 folders) (Box 16)
      - Why women work, 1979-1981 (Box 16)
      - Will it continue, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Children, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Cohabitation and other alternatives to marriage, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Corporate women, 1983-1988 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Divorce, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Doyle Dane study, 1979 (Box 16)
    - ERA (Equal Rights Ammendment), 1980-1981 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Ethnic markets, 1983-1988 and undated (Box 17)
    - Family, 1977-1990 and undated
      - General, 1977-1980 (Box 17)
      - American family, 1985-1990 (Box 17)
      - Family and work, 1988-1990, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Food habits of Far Eastern children, undated (Box 17)
    - Glass ceiling, circa 1985-1993, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Hispanic marketing, 1989 and undated (Box 17)
    - Ideal lifestyle questions, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Impact of working women, 1986-1989 and undated (Box 17)
    - Marriage, 1977-1980 and undated (Box 17)
    - Men, 1987-1992 and undated (Box 17)
    - Miscomprehension, 1980-1987 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Moving Target, 1976-1977
      - Book proposal, undated (Box 18)
      - Page proofs, notes, chapters 1-16 and afterword, undated (Box 18)
    - New demographics, 1976, (6 folders) (Box 19)
      - Beyond demographics, 1984 (Box 19)
      - New demographic questions, 1984 (Box 19)
      - Understanding the New Demographics, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Over forty-nine, 1976-1991 and undated, (6 folders)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 19)
      - Media analysis, 1976-1991 (Box 19)
    - Partnership adjustments, 1977-1980 and undated (Box 20)
    - Partnership husbands, undated (Box 20)
    - Pre-Testing, undated (Box 20)
    - Professional women and men, 1993 (Box 20)
    - Sex role: stereotypes, 1988-1992, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Social class: husband attitudes, undated (Box 20)
    - Status of women, 1989-1994 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 20)
    - Teens, 1988-1992 and undated (Box 20)
    - Trends, 1987-1995 and undated
      - Advertising trends, 1987-1995 (Box 20)
      - Australia, undated (Box 20)
      - International consumer trends, 1985-1995 (Box 20)
      - Social trends, 1985-1995 (Box 20)
    - United Nations (UN) (Box 21)
      - Women, 1974 (Box 21)
      - Women in Latin America, 1988-1989, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - What it means to marketers, 1976-1981 and undated, (6 folders) (Box 21)
    - Why women work, 1978-1981 and undated (Box 21)
    - Women and advertising, 1978-1982, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - Women and media, 1985-1992, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Women and politics, 1985-1992 (Box 22)
    - Women and society
      - Authority figures, 1977-1980 (Box 22)
      - Corporate, 1978-1980 (Box 22)
      - Currently unassigned, 1977-1981 (Box 22)
      - Future, 1977-1980 (Box 22)
      - How they see their lives, 1980 (Box 22)
      - Life cycle, 1977-1980 (Box 22)
      - Media, 1980 (Box 22)
      - Politics, 1978-1980, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Women at work, 1974, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - Women entrepreneurs, 1986-1992 (Box 23)
    - Women industry, 1977-1981 (Box 23)
    - Women in:
      - Afghanistan, undated (Box 23)
      - Africa, undated (Box 23)
      - Canada, 1988-1993 (Box 23)
      - China, 1992 (Box 23)
      - Great Britain, 1976-1990 (Box 23)
      - Italy, 1987 (Box 23)
      - Ireland, 1990-1993 (Box 23)
      - Japan, 1988-1995 (Box 23)
      - Latin America, 1986-1988 (Box 23)
      - Russia, 1989 (Box 23)
      - Scandinavia, 1985-1991 (Box 23)
      - Spain, 1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's aspirations, undated (Box 23)
    - Women's City Club of New York, 1988-1993 (Box 23)
    - Women's market, 1986-1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's movement, 1985-1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's role, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Working women (Box 24)
      - Australia, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Austria, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Belgium, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Brazil, 1970s (Box 24)
      - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 24)
      - Denmark, 1974 (Box 24)
      - General, 1970s-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 24)
      - International Overview, 1974 and undated (Box 24)
      - Italy, 1973-1974 (Box 24)
      - Japan, 1968-1974 (Box 24)
      - Product Use, 1970s (Box 24)
      - South Africa, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Sweden, 1974 (Box 24)
      - United Kingdom, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970s-1990s (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1992, (1-2 of 9 folders) (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1992, (3-9 of 9 folders) (Box 25)
  - Published Materials subseries, 1970s-1996 and undated
    Includes publications related to Bartos' own work, but not written by her. Arranged alphabetically.
    - 1990s and Beyond, 1990 (Box 25)
    - 1977 Yankelovich Special Report, 1977 (Box 25)
    - Advertising for Women Under 49: Six TV Commercials, 1983 (Box 25)
    - American Women in International Women's Year, 1975 (Box 25)
    - Arab as Consumer: Arab Attitudes on Trade and the Advertising Media, undated (Box 25)
    - AWNY Report
      - A Study of Women and Men in the Advertising/Communications Industry, 1993 (Box 25)
      - Press Coverage on The AWNY Report as of June 7,1993, 1993 (Box 25)
    - Cleo Three S Report on Self, Status and Sexuality, undated (Box 26)
    - Cosmopolitan Report on the Changing Life Course of American Women, (vol. 1-3), 1985-1987 (Box 26)
    - Creative Approach Test, undated (Box 26)
    - Decade of Women: A Ms. History of the Seventies in Words and Pictures, 1980 (Box 26)
    - Esquire: A Celebration of the New American Woman, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Gallup Study of Attitudes Towards Advertising, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Global Dynamics-Glass Ceiling: Perception or Reality, undated (Box 26)
    - J.D. Power and Associates 1996 Media Power Report, 1996 (Box 26)
    - Ladies Home Journal American Woman Survey, 1992 (Box 27)
    - J. Walter Thompson Reports
      - Advertising in Black America, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Advertising to Women: The Impact of Employment and Life-Style on the Media Behavior of Women, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Creative Development Program, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Crisis in Branding, 1978 (Box 27)
      - Communications Capability of J. Walter Thompson Company, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Communications Research Viewpoint on Concept Testing, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Do-It-Yourself Workbook for Developing a Moving Target Presentation, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Exploration of the Attitudes of Marine Wives Towards the Marine Wives Retention Booklet, 1973 (Box 27)
      - Special Markets Group, circa 1971 (Box 27)
    - Roper Reports Index, 1973-1986, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Virginia Slims American Women's Opinion Poll, 1980-1990 (Box 27)
    - Whirlpool Foundation Study:, 1995-1996 (Box 28)
      - Women, New Priorities, 1995 (Box 28)
      - Women, New Providers, 1996 (Box 28)
    - Woman's Place: Changing Place of Women in Britain, 1986 (Box 28)
    - Women, Work, and Markets of the 80's, 1979 (Box 28)
    - Women's Campaign Research Fund: Women Leaders for a Change, 1970s (Box 28)
    - Working Women 1980-1985: An Emerging Market, circa 1980 (Box 28)
    - Working Women, April 1972, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Working Women, Social Values Perspectives, 1980 (Box 28)
    - Working Woman Study, 1985 (Box 28)
    - Working Woman Study: Cities Edition, undated (Box 28)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1977-1990 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Consists of audio and visual copies of presentations or interviews given by Bartos. Includes tape recordings of interviews from Bartos' work on The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research, promotional work and interviews, and videotaped copies of speeches given by Bartos.
  Restriction Note: Originals and Reference Master copies are closed to patron use. Patrons should consult Use Copies available in collection.
  - Originals (CLOSED)
    - Videocassettes (Box 29)
      - OR1. Aging Project, 1983. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR2. Rio de Janeiro, 1980. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR3. Founding Fathers of Research, undated. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR4. The Moving Target, 1977. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR5. Women Say the Darndest Things, 1983. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR6. Breakfast Speaker, 1990. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR7. Images of Women in Advertising, 1989. VHS-M. (Box 29)
      - OR8. WPP Group Plc, undated. VHS. (Box 29)
    - Audio cassettes